A Guide to the Asia Society records FA110
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Special Formats - General, 1921-1981; 1960-1978; 15
  - Moving Images, 3; 13 film reels 13 films on 16mm and 35mm film.
    - An Interview with Indira Gandhi, 1975; Sound, Color, 28 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1781)
      FROM A CANADIAN NEWS SOURCE, A PROFILE OF INDIAN PRIME MINISTER INDIRA GANDHI. SHOWN AT WORK AND AT HOME, THE EPISODE DISCUSSES GANDHI'S CAREER AND CURRENT STRUGGLES WITH POWER, AMIDST A STATE OF EMERGENCY AND ACCUSATIONS OF TYRANNY. DIRECTED AND PRODUCED BY PAUL SALTZMAN; A SUNRISE FILMS LTD PRODUCTION (1975)
    - Chess, Sound, Color, 30 seconds; 16mm film (Reel AV 2252)
      30 second TV publuic service spot promoting volunteer recruitment for the Mayor's Voluntary Action Center.
  - Moving Images - Tassilo Adam films, 1921-1928; 4; 64 film reels Tassilo Adam film collection encompasses approximately 25,000 feet of film on 64 reels.
    Biographical / Historical
    Tassilo Adam (1878-1955) was a German-born ethnographer who was appointed the official Ethnologist of the Dutch East Indies by the Governor General of Java. He was a photographer and amateur filmmaker with an anthropological and documentary approach to the Indonesian culture he captured on film. From 1929-1955, Adam was the curator of Oriental Art at the Brooklyn Museum.
    Tassilo Adam film collection encompasses approximately 25,000 feet of film on 64 reels. The collection includes dupe negatives and prints in 16mm and 35mm formats.
    Many reels contain duplicate content with varying image quality. Java Reels 1-11 contain superior image quality, as they are believed to have been copied straight from the nitrate original. Other reels are duplicates several generations away from original source. Many are believed to have been edited by Adam for presentational purposes.
    The documentary footage was shot in Indonesia from 1921-1928 of dances, shadow play, dramatic dance, religious processions, wedding festivals in the palaces, and other ceremonies as well as dance finery, costumes of the Javanese nobles, everyday wear and dance attire. The bulk of the collection is of Central Java, comprising of court ceremonies and dances at the palaces of Jogyakarta and Surakarta, as well as village performances and rituals in the surrounding area.
    Highlights of the collection include the films that capture
    • Wayang Wong, a type of classical Javanese dance theatrical performance with themes taken from episodes of the Ramayana or Mahabharata
    • Wayang Topeng, a Javanese theatrical performance in which performers wear masks.
    • Kuda Kepang or Kuda Lumping, a traditional Javanese dance depicting a group of horsemen.
    • Serimpi, a classical dance of Cental Java associated with royal palaces of Yogyakarta and Surakarta. The dance epitomizes the character of the royal court, and the dance became an important symbol of the ruler's power as well as the refinement of Javanese culture.
    • Bedoyo dances, is a ritualized dance of Java and is associated with the royal palaces of Yogyakarta and Surakarta. The dance epitomizes the character of the royal court, and the dance became an important symbol of the ruler's power.
    • Wayang Kulit, a Javanese shadow puppet theatrical performance
    • Gamelan, a traditional orchestra of Java and Bali in Indonesia, made up predominantly of percussive instruments.
    Films are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Arts and Crafts, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes.; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2273)
      Scenes of brass production, weaving and fabric working, wood carving and ceremonial procession with traditional costume, performance and music.
    - Awakening, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 18 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2276)
      Scenes of city life including automobiles driving down city streets, a parrot eating corn, man with pet baboon trained to knock coconuts off of trees, man in a field exercising and people rowing canoes down a river. Additional footage of Lembak people of Indonesia watering animals, playing in water, woman combing each others' hair, village life and people walking down city streets.
    - Badayo Solo, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2323)
      Scenes of gamelan orchestra, people in animal costumes, group of female court dancers.
    - Ballon Bedoyos, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2329)
      Scenes of a group of female court dancers and gamelon orchestra. Various scences of market life and harvesting.
    - Bodoyo Dancers I, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2343)
      Group of female court dancers, large temple and court musicans. Intertitle cards in Dutch.
      There is a film puncture through the first half of reels. Mediocre image quality.
    - Bodoyo Dancers II, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2344)
      Large temple - looks like Buddhist; musicians; group of female court dancers.
      Mediocre image quality.
    - Boli, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 12 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2345)
      Ceremonial dance in costume (masks, dragon), without costume/female in costume/musicans/male in costume (mask and robes)/group of dancers (masks and robes), close-ups/warriors dancing (ceremonial)/ ceremonial fingernails on female/cockfight. Footage of men hydrating and keeping cool.
    - Boli 2, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 5 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2342)
      Footage of man and boy's faces acknowledging the camera. Westerns being greeted, female court dancers, sword handles, faces, shrines, view of countryside, shrine, and cockfight.
    - Bull Races, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes; Footage of festivals, dancing, important people leaving in automobiles and shaking hands with others outside, arrival by car to the bull racing festivals, and bull's decorations.; 16mm film (Reel AV 2339)
    - Celebes VII, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2328)
      Scenes of map showing route and stops, Welcome arch, people lined up waving, warrior dances, parade, island views, waterfall, harbor, passenger liner at the dock, "mansion", old fort, temple, speed boat, shoreline, cliffs, ceremonial dance, village market.
    - Count Sola, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2318)
      Scenes of royal procession, military troop manuevers with rifles, gamelan performance, wayang performance, dancers performing outside and warrior dance.
    - Court Djogjakarta, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2317)
      Scenes of the sultan with intertitle cards describing actions. Intertitle cards: "His Highness the Sultan of Jogjakarta, Hamangku Buwono VIIL (Hamengkubuwono VIII ?)"; "The Gooningana (gifts) are carried to the mosque to be blessed."; "The regenis and the High Council or their way to the Mosque."
    - Court of Solo, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2321)
      Scenes with intertitles. Intertitles read: "The archers of the body guard of the Susuhunan."; "Bearers of the holy weapons, golden ornaments etc. of past ages."; "The golden throne of the Susuhunan."; "The Susuhunan (Emperor) of Surakarta with the resident." Scenes of military troop manuevers with rifles.
    - Court [Repeats] and Village Life, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2271)
      Footage of Indonesia cort procession, military drills, traditional costume and important people (military, religious, social) and scenes of rural village life including field work, women crafting, creating and working with fabric, men creating crockery and plowing rice rices with oxen.
    - Crafts, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2340)
      Footage of brass production, a few scenes of wood carving. Film is erratically spliced with many duplicate scenes. Intertitle cards in Dutch.
    - Dancer Court, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2326)
      Scenes of female dancers dancing, and displaying and modeling costumes for the camera. Male dancers stick fighting, dancing with lancings and play fighting.
    - Dancing XI, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 29 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2306)
      Footage of warriors in traditional costume dress. Boys and young men excerising by jumping over walls and dancing to gongs. Includes scenes of warrior dance, chiefs, ironmongs, making cloth, bathing a baby, female making flour, children playing a ballgame, chief and warriors assembled, children going to school, carrying water, four men making flour, cutting coconuts, greeting people, man getting lip cut, warriors marching and dancing, showing fighting technique, village assembly, and butchering.
    - Dancing XI: Bali-Java, circa 1920s; 16mm film; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes (Reel AV 2278)
      Ceremonial dance in costume (masks, dragon); warrior dance with gamelan orchestra, woman dancing without costume; male musicians and dancers in costume (mask and robes). Scene of a group of masked and robed dancers. Close-ups of ceremonial warrior dance and ceremonial fingernails on a woman. Scene of a man with a pet baboon trained to climb trees and knock down coconuts.
    - Dutch Ship, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 12 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2272)
      Harbor scenes, small sailing craft, barges, passengers debarking, rickshaws, city scenes. Footage of the Dutch ocean liner Pieter Corneliszoon Hooft.
    - Farmers, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 18 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2338)
      Footage of plowing with oxen in rice paddies; view of rice terraces; rice planting; rice harvesting; ox carts transporting rice; and cutting sugar cane.
    - Funeral, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2324)
      Scenes of the funeral of the sultan, funerary procession, crowds of people walking and carrying the coffin of the sultan, horse drawn carriages, people climbing up and down stairs.
    - Horse Dance, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2320)
      Kuda Kepang (horse trance dance). Shows dancers on rattan horses, the Garuda bird, Barong monster, and a dancer who falls into a deep trance. Same content as AV 2283; shots appear to be edited into performance order.
    - Instruments, Shadow Puppets, Dancers, and Processions (Reel L), circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2274)
      Footage of Indonesia wedding ceremony with the Sultan as a guest. Scenes of wedding procession and footage of Wayang, Javanese shadow puppet theater with gamelan orchestra. Dutch and Englishs intertitles.
    - Java - Reel 1, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2300)
      Scenes of female dancers performing choreography, examples of dancers' head dress, competition with oxen. Includes Dutch intertitles.
    - Java - Reel 2, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2301)
      Includes scenes of female dancers practing choreography, farmers reveal how agriculture is done, picking wheat stalks, farmers cleaning wheat in the water, attaching an ox to a cart. Footage of farmland, bowl manufactures, sign reads "Kunstarbeid djokja", example of worthy posessions.
    - Java - Reel 3, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2303)
      Includes scenes of a view of Sanitarium Tosari, men smoking cigarettes, a volcano, children, social dancing, moving possessions out of a house, slaughtering a goat, villagers, mountain statues, a parade, villagers traveling around the mountain and land, and soldiers standing at attention and marching.
    - Java - Reel 4, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 12 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2302)
      Footage of sailboats from a ship at sea, docks and the shore, passengers stepping off of the boat Pieter Corneliszoon Hooft, long shot of city from view of ship. Footage of what the boat passes on its trip, examples of smaller modes of transportation inside the city, view of the land from the boat.
    - Java - Reel 5, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2299)
      Footage of a train, basin and mountains, volcano, landscape scenery shots, view of the Sanitorium (outside only).
    - Java - Reel 6, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2298)
      Includes scenes of men carrying pyramid structures (tomb or coffin?), man showing fine fabrics or clothing, procession with gifts and soldiers entering with spears.
    - Java - Reel 7, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2297)
      Includes scenes of two men dancing, a female dancer, a village market and the making and selling of food. Footage of fabric working, laundring, dying and retouching, 2 dancers and the band that provides their music. Includes Dutch intertitles.
    - Java - Reel 8, circa 1920s; 35mm film (Fine grain); Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes (Reel AV 2282)
      Scenes of military maneuvers, and military procession with Dutch colonials.
    - Java - Reel 9 (Asia), circa 1920s; 35mm film (Fine grain); Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes (Reel AV 2283)
      Kuda Kepang (horse trance dance). Shows dancers on rattan horses, the Garuda bird, Barong monster, and a dancer who falls into a deep trance. Also male dancers fighting with spears and shields. Contains Dutch intertitles.
    - Java - Reel 10, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2296)
      Scenes of a state coach transport being lead by soldiers, a train bringing the coffin to the Imogiri (a royal grave complex in Yogyakarta in south-central Java), footage of massive stair paths, young females acknowledging the camera, male dancers with sticks, puppetry making, gamelan orchestra playing, and a wayang puppetry performance. Footage includes Dutch intertitles.
    - Java - Reel 11, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 11 minutes; 35mm film (Fine grain) (Reel AV 2295)
      Footage of marketplace selling hats, baskets, food, women with children, communal cooking, crowd with flags, women and men carrying gifts under rain cover. Includes Dutch intertitles.
    - Java Street, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2308)
      Street scenes of Java featuring people walking and holding flags.
    - Keraton Surakarta Dan Sekitarnya, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 32 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2334)
      Includes footage of hand motions and dancing, possible theatrical storytelling related to battles and fighting, footage of procession as extravogent carriage arrives, temple on a mountain, soldiers in shooting practice, community meeting presenting gifts to a leader, wayang shadow puppet show, gamelon orchestra accompanys wayang performance, young women posing and laughing in front of the camera, and additional footage of women dancing and rehearsing.
    - Keraton Yogyakarta Dan Sekitarnya, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 40 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2336)
      Scenes of dignitaries saying goodbye then driving off, village buildings and surroundings, communal cooking practices, woodworking, metalworking, village manufacturing, bowlmaking. Villagers show off their handiwork, parade procession, seaside, villagers take posessions out to the water, villagers showing interest and curiosity about the camera, dancers display head dress, musicans playing. Community gathers to see variety of performances by adults and children. Footage of animal costumes, performers showing off faces and makeup, child performers, children swimmining in a pool, young men as scouts being watched by a crowd, parachute/hot air balloon, outfits of soldiers, crowd carrying pyramids with military fanfare.
    - Love Dance - A, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 12 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2309)
      Scenes of gamelan orchestra, male costumed dancers performing, drawves dancing, people dancing in various costumes- skeletons, birds, dragons, boar, snake, oxen, elephant, deer and panther.
    - Love Dance, Horse Dance, Shadow Puppets, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2325)
      Scenes of gamelan orchestra, couple dancing, horse dance, performers in masks, creating puppets for shadow puppet theater performance, shadow puppet theater performed.
    - Madura, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2314)
      Footage of Madura Island off the Northeast coast of Java in Indonesia. Scenes of people getting in and out of cars, bronze working, weaving, street scenes, and temple scuplture relief.
    - Markets and Streets, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 5 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2341)
      Footage of men women and children walking through the streets acknowledging the camera, cooking in the market, purchasing hats, baskets and portable water jugs. Intertitle cards in Dutch.
    - Multiple Java Scenes (Can G22N), circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2315)
      Scenes of people getting in and out of cars, processions, bull racing, children swimming, fabric working.
    - Multiple Java Scenes (NIAS), circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 17 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2331)
      Scenes of people in costumes, warriors with weapons exercising, children dancing to gongs, warrior dance, chiefs, ironmongs, making cloth, bathing a baby, female making flous, children playing a ballgame, chief and warriors assembled, children going to school, carrying water, four men making flour, cutting coconuts, greeting people, man getting lip cut, warriors marching and dancing, showing fighting techniques, village assembly, and butchering.
    - Nature Life, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 16 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2275)
      Scenes of Indonesian landscapes, people climbing mountains, village life, rice farming, and village markets.
    - Painter Speis, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 13 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2330)
      Scenes of outdoor footage, temples, clowns, mountain tops, costumed people in masks sitting.
    - Pram Banan, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2327)
      Scenes of markets, temples, temple statues, scultural relief, warriors dancing and stick fighting.
    - Soldiers - Court / Hair Ceremony (R-11), circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2319)
      Scenes of military procession.
    - Solo Sultan, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 27 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2310)
      Scenes of young girls, horse drawn carriages, royal processions, men doing military manuevers with rifles, canons bring fired and marching band.
    - Sugar Plantation I, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2290)
      Scenes of plantation workers' housing, fields, workers, plantation houses, Ford Model T driving on roadways, village (company town), school children, church, hospital, doctor at work, operation room, island road, view of mountains, river and waterfall.
    - Sugar Plantation II, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 14 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2291)
      Scenes of people working in the sugar cane fields, transportation of sugar cane on trains and ox carts, processing sugar cane for shipment, loading on frieghts, warehouse and plantation houses, industrial machinery processing sugar cane in a refinery.
    - Sultan's Court, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2311)
      Scenes of dancing, musicans, people getting in and out of cars, and royal procession.
    - Tassilo Adam compilation film I, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 38 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2335)
      Scenes of male/female couple dancing with a band in the background, male/female dancers modeling their costume and head gear. Includes Java - Reel 8 (AV 2282 ). Procession of community bringing gifts, soldiers at shooting practice, intertitles about children as little soldiers, footage of the Susuhunan, archers, the golden throne. Includes "Painter Speis". Footage of animal costume, parachute/hot air balloon, people bringing statues to the mountain, crowd carrying cone shaped monuments down the street. Includes "Court DJO-VG Karta". Includes scenes of elders modeling wardrobes and hats, albino villager. Intertitles about the Sultan's officials, Eldest Pangeran, Assistant Resident, His Highness the Sultan of Jogjakarta, Hamangku Buwono III, Gooningans (gifts).
    - Tassilo Adam compilation film II, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2347)
    - Temples (Reel 8), circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2307)
      Footage of temples, statues, scupltures, reliefs and relics. Scene of excavators in temple. Temple dedicated to Brahma and Temple of Shiva are featured in the footage.
    - Wong Dancers, circa 1920s; Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes; 16mm film (negative) (Reel AV 2322)
      Scenes of villagers and Wayang wong dancers, a classical Javanese dance theaterical performance.